<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Seasonable advice to youth A funeral sermon on Psal. 119. 9. Preach'd upon the death of Mr. Richard Walter, jun. In the eighteenth year of his age. January 13th, 1691/2. By John Shower.</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60149</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220294</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831714</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831714</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36181</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60149)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36181)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2098:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Seasonable advice to youth A funeral sermon on Psal. 119. 9. Preach'd upon the death of Mr. Richard Walter, jun. In the eighteenth year of his age. January 13th, 1691/2. By John Shower.</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Samuel Crouch, at the corner of Pope's-Head-Alley, over against the Royal-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1: A funeral sermon on the death of Mr. Richard Walter.</note>
                  <note>Copy closely trimmed at foot with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Walter, Richard, d. 1692 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36181:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Seaſonable Advice to Youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Funeral Sermon</hi> On <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.9.</p>
            <p>Preach'd upon the DEATH OF Mr. Richard Walter, Jun.</p>
            <p>In the Eighteenth Year of his Age.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>January</hi> 13th, 1691/2.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN SHOWER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Crouch,</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Pope</hi>'s-<hi>Head-Alley,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:36181:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36181:2"/>
            <head>TO Mr. <hi>JOHN WALTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF the following Sermon upon the Death of your Brother, may be of any <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Advantage unto others, the Obligation will be very much owing to you, with whoſe Deſire I complied in the Preaching of it, and now in the making of it Publick: The chief of my Deſign therein being the Inſtruction of the Younger ſort, I could not ſo fitly prefix any other Name as yours. I hope your tender Affection to your Brother will make you read this Memorial of of him with great Seriouſneſs; and aſſiſt your good Improvement of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, which are ſo needful for Perſons of your Age to conſider, and obey.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36181:3"/>
            <p>I ſhall only add my Hearty Prayer to God for the Early Impreſſions of his Grace, to Sanctifie you betimes, and make you to know and love the Holy Scriptures, and ſo preſerve you from the Snares of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, and particularly from Youthful Luſts.</p>
            <p>If this Sermon may any way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to ſuch a deſirable effect on you, and others of your Age, I ſhall bleſs God.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London,
<date>
                     <hi>Feb. 25. 1691/2.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I am Yours, in the beſt Services,</hi> John Shower.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36181:3"/>
            <head>A Funeral SERMON On the DEATH of Mr. <hi>Richard Walter.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm. 119.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Wherewithal ſhall a Young Man cleanſe his way? By taking Heed <hi>thereto</hi> according to thy Word.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>A Practical Diſcourſe to Young Perſons would not be unfit at any Time, in this Age, and in this City, if there were no ſpecial Occaſion leading to it: But it is moſt fit, when there is one, ſuch as the Providence of God hath now given me, by the <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Funeral</hi> of a Young Gentleman. What I ſhall ſay on <hi>that Subject,</hi> I reſerve for the Cloſe, to inforce the Improvement of <hi>the other</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this Text: Which will admit to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered two ways. Either</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> As the rectifying and cleanſing the way of Youth, is a neceſſary <hi>Means</hi> in order to the obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God's Word, and the keeping his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:36181:4"/> The Original will bear this Interpretation: And ſome Ancient Verſions do countenance it. The Senſe then is this, How ſhall Young Men be purged and purified by Divine Grace, ſo as thereby to be qualified for Obedience to God? It is a kind of Prayer (in a Poetick ſtrain) for that Grace which is neceſſary to Holy Walking. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I chuſe rather to conſider thoſe Words, as an Anſwer to the Enquiry, <hi>by what means</hi> we may be ſanctified betimes, and enabled to pleaſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God in our whole Courſe. And that we are told, is by carefully obſerving, and <hi>taking heed to the Word of God:</hi> The Bleſſed Influence whereof to that purpoſe is here Aſſerted and Amplified. Partly from the <hi>Subject,</hi> with reſpect to whom it hath this Effect, <hi>A Young Man.</hi> Partly from the ſpecial Object, about which this purifying Influence of the Divine Word is employed, in ſuch an one, <hi>i. e. The Cleanſing of his way.</hi> This extends to all that needs to be rectified either in Heart or Life, in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit or Practice: Not only as to his external Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, but his inward Principles and Temper. For we read of the Young Man's walking <hi>in the way of his own Heart,</hi> and in the ſight of his own Eyes, Eccl. xi. 9.</p>
            <p>Neither are we to over-look the Form and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Expreſſion, by way of <hi>Question, Wherewithal ſhall a Young Man cleanſe his way?</hi> The Pſalmiſt had before declared the Deſire of his Soul, that his Life might be ordered according to God's Word.<note place="margin">Ver. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Oh that my ways were directed to keep thy Statutes!</hi> He had profeſſed the Purpoſe and Reſolution of his Heart to endeavour it.<note place="margin">Ver. 8.</note> 
               <hi>I will keep thy Statutes, O forſake
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36181:4"/> me not utterly!</hi> Upon which follows the Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Text, <hi>Wherewithal,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> But how ſhall one ſo Young as I am, under the Guidance of a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Mind, and the Biaſs of Corrupt and Vicious Inclinations, aſſiſted with very little Experience, ſurrounded with many dangerous Examples, and ſuitable Temptations, <hi>&amp;c. How,</hi> or <hi>wherewithal</hi> ſhall <hi>ſuch a One</hi> be Cleanſed, and Reformed, and Enabled to pleaſe and obey God? The Anſwer is, by attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Inſtructions of his Word, by obſerving the Orders and Directions he hath there given us, by applying that Word for our Sanctification, and by following the Holy Counſels and Conduct of it.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion it ſelf how this may be done, doth ſuppoſe the <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> and imply the <hi>Difficulty</hi> of it. There is great need it ſhould be done; but how ſhall it be effected? Were it not a matter of ſome Difficulty, there would be no ground for ſuch a Queſtion, <hi>by what means</hi> it may be brought about. But becauſe it is not a ſlight and eaſie, though moſt needful matter, the proper means muſt be diligently ſought for, and minded, <hi>viz. by taking heed unto the Word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the opening of this Paſſage, there are <hi>Four things</hi> to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The ſinful ways of Youth, that need to be Rectified and Cleanſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Difficulty that is ſuppoſed by the Interrogation, to Purifie and Reform them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The ſufficient and only means how this may be done, <hi>i. e.</hi> by the Word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Neceſſity of careful Attendance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Word, and particular Application of it, to an effectual Cure.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:36181:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Concerning the ſinful impure ways of Youth, which need to be Rectified and Cleanſed. The Corruption of Human Nature upon the the Firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy, is not more plainly expreſſed in the Divine Revelation, than manifeſt in the effects of it, unto the experience of all, who are any ways acquainted with themſelves. We need but compare what we find in our ſelves with the Holy Image, Nature, and Law of God unto which at firſt there was a juſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity and Agreement in the Nature of Man. But now we are alienated from God, and diſaffected to him: The inward and deep depravation of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding</hi> and <hi>Will,</hi> the Two Superior Powers of the Soul, that command the reſt, may eaſily be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, if we will but examine and reflect upon our ſelves.<note place="margin">Tit. 3.3.</note> That our Judgments are deceived, and our Minds blinded, and our Wills fetter'd by Senſual Luſts, and that we are pleaſed with our Slavery, and unwilling to be delivered. The Rectitude of our Nature being loſt by the Firſt Tranſgreſſion, an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary Corruption, is tranſmitted from our Firſt Parents to all their Poſterity. <hi>We are ſhapen in Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and conceived in Sin: And that which is born of the Fleſh is Fleſh. Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean?</hi> This diſcovers it ſelf very early in Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and with more violence in the various Luſts of Youth, according to the ſeveral circumſtances of their Conditions in the World, and the different Channel that is formed for it by their particular Conſtitutions and Tempers. The moſt principal Duties and Inſtitutions of Chriſtianity, do ſuppoſe this Degeneracy and Corruption of Human Nature; and in this and many other Scriptures, it is manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly implyed. The Subject of this Text is not Pure
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36181:5"/> and Unbiaſſed, equally indifferent unto Good or Evil, but 'tis ſuppoſed that he needs to be purified, as well as guided. <hi>Wherewithal ſhall a Young Man cleanſe his way? His way cleanſed:</hi> There is hardly any Metaphor whereby the Affections and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of Men are more uſually expreſſed, than by this of their <hi>Way</hi> and <hi>Walk:</hi> But there are ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ways of Wickedneſs more appropriate unto <hi>Youth,</hi> than to Elder Perſons. The Inſtructions, Counſels and Exhortations of the Holy Scriptures, (beſides thoſe of common and univerſal Concern,) are therefore all ſuited to the various Claſſes under which Men may be ſeverally conſidered. There are ſome corrupt Inclinations and Practices, ſome ways of Sin to which <hi>Young Men</hi> are more inclined and tempted than before or after that Age: which in Childhood they are not arrived unto, and in Riper Years are commonly exchanged for others: I ſay <hi>commonly,</hi> becauſe ſometimes Gray Hairs are deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Vices and Follies of Youth; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Wiſdom and Virtue of Old Age may be Eminently the Ornament of Young Men. Old Age may ſometimes <hi>flouriſh</hi> in Youth, and be as often <hi>periſhed</hi> in thoſe that are well ſtricken in Years. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs for inſtance, is not ſo much the Peculiar Vice of the Age, but may be the Fault of Young Perſons. The <hi>Rich Young Man</hi> in the Goſpel is an Inſtance, who told our Lord, that he had kept the Commandments. But he had Houſes, and Lands, and Bags of Mony, which ſtood in his way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, thoſe he obſerved, and kept as well as the Commandments. Particular Countries and Places, particular Callings and Relations, particular Seaſons and Times may have their ſpecial Sins; and ſo have
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36181:6"/> the different Ages of Men. The Ignorance of Youth is commonly attended with Pride and Conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For they who know but a few things, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways moſt preſumptuous of their own Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo are commonly more Raſh and Haſty, Giddy and Inconſtant, fond of Liberty, and Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of Reſtraint, Affecters of Novelty, and Lovers of Pleaſure, of Company, Paſtime, and ſenſual Mirth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There are ſome youthful Luſts, which young <hi>Timothy</hi> is warned againſt,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.22.</note> ſuch as Ambition and Vain-glory, Curioſity, and Envy to appear Great and conſiderable before others, as the Scope of the Place, and three or four following Verſes ſeem to manifeſt. Not <hi>Drunkenneſs</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or ſuch carnal Luſts. For tho' all Men have the Seeds of theſe, yet the Modeſty and Frugality, the Weakneſs of Conſtitution, and often Infirmities of <hi>Timothy</hi> make it very improbable they ſhould here be principally meant. The Corruption of Human Nature, 'tis true, doth uſually and with great Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence diſcover it ſelf in unſanctified Youth, by <hi>theſe Luſts</hi> of the Fleſh, Theſe are ſome of the ways of their Heart, according to which they form their Lives: Where the Reſtraint of Bodily Temper, ſpecial Providence, Religious Education, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace do not make the difference. I need not go about to prove that <hi>Childhood and Youth are Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, or Sinful Folly,</hi> conſidering the many Examples in Scripture, and the multitude of ſuch in every Age, and in none more than our own; conſidering the frequent Warnings given us by God againſt ſuch Luſts; conſidering the bitter Remorſes, and peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Confeſſions of many who are truly Converted, or but Awakned by the proſpect of Death and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36181:6"/> conſidering the earneſt Supplications even of Good Men, that God would not <hi>Remember the Sins of their Youth.</hi> Even <hi>David</hi> thought he had cauſe for ſuch a Requeſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.7. whoſe Poverty and Piety, whoſe Induſtry and Afflictive Trials in his Younger Years, were a very great Reſtraint from thoſe Luſts which are more Unbridled in others of another Education and Condition. Not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion how many in Riper Years are made to <hi>paſſeſs the Sins of their Youth,</hi> Job 13.26. <hi>and their very Bones are full of them,</hi> Job 20.11. For a Young Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hath himſelf for his <hi>Heir</hi> and <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> when he is Old; and that which he receives for his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, is only the ſorrowful remembrance and bitter Fruits of his Youthful Follies.</p>
            <p>It is ſad to conſider how many Young Men of hopeful Parts, and promiſing Capacities, are taken in the Devils Snares, in the purſuit of Senſual Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; and lay up Matter for future Diſeaſes, and bodily Pains; how they poiſon their Blood, and weaken their Conſtitutions; how they haſten or antedate the Infirmities of Old Age, and do what they can to dig their own Graves. But it is a more Melancholly Reflection, to conſider how they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God, and incenſe his Almighty Vengeance; how they wound and wrong their own Souls, and treaſure up Wrath againſt the Day of Wrath; how they provide Fuel for everlaſting Fire, and conſign their Bodies and Souls to Hell for ever. To ſee them run headlong to their own deſtruction, by walking in the way of their Hearts, and in the ſight of their own Eyes: To conſider how eaſily, they are led into deſtructive Paths, and made a cheap and haſty Prey by the Tempter, till they are hardned
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36181:7"/> paſt Recovery, or cut off in the midſt of their days, by a ſudden Arreſt of Judgment. And ſo for the ſhort and vain Pleaſures of Youth, they periſh to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity;</hi> unleſs ſome few of them by an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Grace are recovered at the laſt Hour, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed unto Saving Repentance: But it is much to be feared, that very few <hi>Death-Bed Penitents</hi> are ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is ſuppoſed to be a matter of no ſmall <hi>Difficulty,</hi> for a Young Man to Reform and Cleanſe his Ways. This in part appears from what hath been ſaid already of the Corruption of Human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the Vicious Inclinations of Youth. Their Ignorance and Raſhneſs, and want of Experience, their Averſion to ſerious Thoughts, for fear of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy;</hi> with the apprehended unſuitableneſs of Reſtraint and Retirement unto Perſons of their Age, do all increaſe the Difficulty. They uſually reckon that they have the World before them, they have Time enough hereafter, and are now in the Age of Liberty and Pleaſure, and that both God and Man will indulge a great deal to <hi>them,</hi> becauſe of their Youth; Preſuming at the ſame time, that <hi>a great while hence,</hi> they ſhall have Opportunity and Heart, and Help, to work out their Salvation when ever they pleaſe. For when they Calculate their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivities, they reckon to the longeſt Term of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Life, that any are wont to reach to. Their Sun is climbing higher, they have a great while to Night, and ſo are far removed from the Thoughts of Death. Accordingly, when ever they are adviſed by thoſe who are <hi>Elder,</hi> to look forward to the Grave, and beyond it, to bethink themſelves of their Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing State, and provide for an Endleſs Life; their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36181:7"/> inward Thought is agreeable to the High-Prieſts An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer unto <hi>Judas, What is that to us, look thou to that.</hi> Such is the Strength and Power of Senſe, and Fancy in the Days of our Youth; ſuch is the Weakneſs of our Reaſon, (as not having attained to any great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency of Judgment, which muſt be ripened by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration and Experience:) ſuch is the violence of our Paſſions, and the Inconſtancy of our Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; ſo variable and uncertain the Objects of our Affections and Choice; ſuch the venomous Influence of <hi>Self-Flattery,</hi> and that of others about us; ſuch the force of Examples, and ſo great the number of ill ones; ſo deep the Impreſſions we receive by the Company we converſe with; (eſpecially if Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or Licentious Youths are the Inſtruments of the Devil to entice us;) ſo little command have we of our ſelves, to bridle thoſe Impetuous Luſts that are eaſily Fired by every Spark of Temptation; and ſo intolerable is the Reproach imagined of being <hi>ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> of not complying with the Cuſtoms of thoſe of the ſame Age with our ſelves, that on theſe and the like Accounts, the Devil hath a mighty Advantage againſt us, in that Portion of our Time.</p>
            <p>For the moſt part, Young Men are Changeable and Unſteady, Heedleſs and Unwary, are but little For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified againſt the Wiles of the Devil; are little uſed to conſider things with any Strength, and Intenſneſs of Thought, and prone to flatter themſelves with fooliſh hopes and projects of the wonderful things which they ſhall be able to compaſs, to do, and be, and enjoy, and reach, before they leave the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That 'tis no wonder that the Principal (becauſe moſt hopeful) Attempts of the Devil are directed againſt ſuch, to deceive and deſtroy them by Youthful
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36181:8"/> Luſts. Children are not capable of doing him ſuch Service, or themſelves ſuch Prejudice, or of being employed to ſo many ill-purpoſes: And commonly Old Men are already fix'd in their way. The Minds of Youth are more flexible, and withal ſharper for any Undertaking; their Bodies ſtronger and more active for moſt kinds of Wickedneſs, their Blood more warm, their Spirits more Vigorous, as their Sinful Deſires are more Raging, and all their Paſſions more vehement. On which account the Wiſdom of the Ancients would not admit Perſons very Young to the Lectures of Moral,<note place="margin">Ariſt. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thic. Lib. 1. Chap. 1.</note> or Civil Philoſophy: as ſuppoſing them to be ſo very much under the Government of their Paſſions, that good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel would be loſt upon them, and all ſuch Diſcourſes prove in vain.</p>
            <p>But though the Philoſophers deſpaired of being able to reclaim and reduce Young Men by their weak and naked Rules of Morality, we need not do ſo, who are under the diſpenſation of a Goſpel of Grace, and are acquainted with the power of the Divine Word. The Precepts of Philoſophy may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt our Recovery from the groſſer Immoralities in practice; ſuch as violate the plain Sentiments of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Conſcience, or are Scandalous in the view of Men. But the Divine Word, (accompanied with the power of the Spirit,) can work an effectual Cure in Heart and Life, by healing our <hi>Corrupt Nature,</hi> and making us partakers of the <hi>Divine.</hi> This is one ſpecial Priviledge of the Goſpel State; and is much for the honour of Divine Grace; recommending at the ſame time the Excellency of the Word of God, as the holy means of it. Which leads us to conſider.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:36181:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That the Word of God is the ſufficient, and only means of Cleanſing and Reforming the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ways of Youth: This Enlightens the Eyes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.6, 7, 8. Pſal. 17.4. Pſal. 37.31. Prov. 6.23.</note> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts the Soul, makes Wiſe the Simple, ſhews us the way of Life, and keeps us from the Paths of the Deſtroyer. It was for this end, that our Bleſſed Lord gave himſelf, <hi>that we might be Sanctified and Cleanſed with the Waſhing of Water, by the Word,</hi> Eph. 5.26. He declared that his Diſciples were <hi>Clean by the Word he had ſpoken to them,</hi> John 15.3. He prays that they might be <hi>Sanctified by the Truth,</hi> which Truth is his <hi>Word;</hi> and makes the ſame Requeſt for all thoſe who ſhould afterwards believe, <hi>John</hi> 17.20.</p>
            <p>And here we might diſtinctly conſider, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are made acquainted with the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of this Sanctification, and Cleanſing: And that by Divine Appointment, this is the ordinary <hi>Means</hi> of effecting it. And farther, that herein the Wiſdom of God is honoured, by its exceeding <hi>Fitneſs</hi> to that end.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Without the knowledge of this Word, we could not fully have underſtood the loathſom Depravity and Corruption of our Hearts, or the manifold Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of our Lives. How wretchedly we are Polluted, and how often we Offend; how Defective are our beſt Duties; how ſhort we come of our Rule and Pattern; and what need there is of ſeeking to recover the Divine Image and Life.</p>
            <p>This Bleſſed Word inſtructs us, how the Ground of our Sanctification is laid in the Satisfaction of Chriſt: how it is procured,<note place="margin">Acts 3.26.</note> and how we may par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of it: What we owe to the Blood of the Croſs, and what to the influence of the Divine Spirit. The Treaſury of Heaven was opened by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36181:9"/> the Sacrifice of Chriſt, that the Holy Spirit might be given to Convince and Convert the World. His <hi>Departure</hi> or <hi>going away,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 15.</note> which comprehend his Death and Aſcenſion, was neceſſary and expedient unto this.</p>
            <p>We are alſo here inſtructed, how this Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is carried on, by our perfecting Holineſs in the Fear of God. For this Water of the Spirit hath a continual Cleanſing Virtue upon all true Chriſtians, until their Purified Souls aſcend to Heaven. He that pitied them when they were in their Pollution, will not leave them after they are Cleanſed, till he hath finiſhed his Work.</p>
            <p>It is from this Word that we are acquainted with the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> and <hi>Extent</hi> of this Sanctification, as reaching to <hi>Soul, Body</hi> and <hi>Spirit.</hi> It tells us the very <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> are defiled; and that there needs not only the Cleanſing of our <hi>Hands,</hi> but the Purifying of our <hi>Hearts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.11, 12, 13, 14.</note> For the Doctrin of the Grace of God, <hi>teacheth us to deny all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Wordly Luſts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">James 4.8.</note> to kill the Luſts of the Eyes, to mortifie the Pride of Life, to crucifie the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the Fleſh, and bring the Underſtanding and Conſcience, and every Thought into Subjection to the Laws of Chriſt.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.1.</note> This tells us what the Filthineſs of <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> is, from which we muſt be Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and how indiſpenſably neceſſary this is to our Acceptance with God, and our Communion with him. This repreſents the Divine Purity, (which we are to imitate and reſemble,) as every way A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable and Excellent. As, that the Bleſſed God eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially hates every Sin, earneſtly forbids it, and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly threatens it, and patiently diſſuades us from it, and ſeverely puniſhes it, and hath mercifully ſent his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36181:9"/> Son to deſtroy this Work of the Devil: Therefore that he <hi>cannot tempt any man to evil,</hi> or neceſſitate and cauſe the Sins of Men, which he warns them againſt on pain of Damnation.</p>
            <p>Never was inward Purity ſo preſſed by any Law before; or the univerſal Sanctification of our Nature advanced to ſuch a pitch. No other Law pretends to reach to the inward Thoughts of the Heart, as thoſe in the Word; which forbids us to Covet, to Luſt, or hate our Brother in our Heart. This ranſacks every filthy Corner, and pierceth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Secrets and Receſſes of every Man's Breaſt; ſpeaking with abſolute Authority to the very Grounds, Principles, and Ends of every Action: diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecting the whole Body of Sin, uncovering the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ulcers of the Soul, manifeſting that a Luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Deſire, impure Mouth, or an unclean Hand, will make a Man polluted before God, and ſtand guilty of the Breach of his Commandment. This Law is exceeding Broad, it forbids not only the ſinful Acts, but the Inſtruments of 'em, what would begin or promote 'em, or is choſen for the Sin's ſake, with relation, or in order to it. This ſhews us whence our Infection did firſt ariſe, tracing it unto its Spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, the firſt Apoſtacy from God; manifeſting the ſpotleſs Holineſs of the Divine Majeſty, and his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect abhorrence of every Sin, ſo as to judge and condemn the inviſible riſings of Diſobedience, and Contrariety to it, in our very <hi>Thoughts.</hi> Yea, by the meaſures of the Goſpel, we are unclean, unleſs we have active Purities. If we are not crucified to the World, we are covetous: we are malicious, and hate our Brother, if we do him not all the Good we can; tho he have treated us injuriouſly;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36181:10"/> we diſhonour the Name of Chriſt, if we do not to our utmoſt advance his Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.13.</note>This is that <hi>Light which maketh manifeſt;</hi> diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that Deformity in Sin, which we never ſaw be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and ſo much of it in the Heart, as we never before believed; with the aggravating Spots of many plauſible Duties, and the provoking circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of our particular Faults. For when we thought our ſelves very <hi>Abſolons</hi> for Beauty, by look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into this Glaſs, we appear as vile and loathſom as Lepers: and all our Secret Sins, which are always in the Light of God's Countenance, are by the Word ſet in order before us. What is ſaid of the Sun in the Heavens, is true of this Word, its Circuit is to the Ends of the Earth, and <hi>there is nothing hid from the Light and Heat thereof.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This may be alſo conſider'd as <hi>the ordinary Means,</hi> which God hath appointed for the cleanſing of our Hearts and Ways. And therefore the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of the Spirit,<note place="margin">1 Pet 1.22. 2 Theſſ. 2.13. Acts 15.9.</note> and believing of the Truth, are joyned together. The Senſe of ſome particular, more notorious Sin, is commonly the firſt means to humble the Soul: When the Charge is brought home by the Word to this or that Perſon, <hi>Thou art the Man,</hi> or <hi>Thou art the Woman,</hi> who haſt ſcorned and ſlighted the Authority of thy Maker, in this or the other Inſtance. Thou art the Fool-hardy Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Creature, who haſt affronted thy Sovereign, who haſt deſpiſed that Goodneſs, which ſhould have led thee to Repentance; abuſed that Patience, which hath a tendency to thy Salvation; rejected that Grace, that would have helped thee; and contemned that Redeemer, who ſhed his Blood for thee. This Voice of the Lord is powerful, to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36181:10"/> ſhake the ſtouteſt Cedars; and make a <hi>Felix</hi> on the Bench to tremble, when preached but by a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner at the Bar. They that Crucified the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and ſcorned his Doctrin, were pierced to the Heart, and cry out, <hi>Men and Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.26. 2 Acts.</note> 
               <hi>what ſhall we do be ſaved!</hi> By this the Chains of the Devil are knock'd off, and his Captives recovered into the Liberty of God's Service. <hi>You ſhall know the Truth,</hi> and <hi>the Truth ſhall make you free, John</hi> 8.32. In this <hi>Jordan</hi> the moſt polluted Creatures have been waſhed; and Hearts full of loathſom Filth have been changed into Veſſels of Purity <hi>Such were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed, but ye are juſtified, but ye are ſanctified,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This therefore is the moſt <hi>likely, fit</hi> and <hi>proper</hi> Means. For beſides, the Encouragement of theſe Examples to ſeek for cleanſing, we have others propounded as our <hi>Patterns</hi> to imitate. Sometimes the Bleſſed God himſelf, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that we may not reſt in low Attainments; and ſometimes the Examples of the Saints, that we might not deſpair of being healed. For the ſame powerful Grace that hath ſanctified others, is able to do the like for us. Therefore while our Impotency and Impurity is declared in this Word, we are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by it to a <hi>Fountain open for ſin, and for unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> We have Promiſes and Precepts moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly connected. What God commands us in one Place as our Duty, he promiſeth to do for us by his Spirit, or enable us to do in another; or at leaſt gives us ground to hope he will.</p>
            <p>Let us then conſider the exceeding great and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Promiſes,</hi> which are the Motives, and Means of our being cleanſed from all Filthineſs of Fleſh and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36181:11"/> Spirit, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. For by them we are made <hi>Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the Divine Nature,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.4.</p>
            <p>It's by this means Divine Impreſſions are made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Soul,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Howe<hi>'s</hi> Bleſſedneſs of the Righteous. <hi>p. 268.</hi>
               </note> the obdurate Heart of a Sinner melted and overcome, and transform'd into the Image of God. Compare this <hi>Means</hi> God works by, with the <hi>Subject</hi> to be wrought upon, and the <hi>Effect</hi> to be wrought, and none can be conceived <hi>fitter.</hi> It is the Office of the Word, by Precepts, Promiſes and Rewards, to inform the Judgment, and awaken Conſcience, and perſuade the Will. It is ſome En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to expect the Influence of the Spirit, in the uſe of this means, becauſe it is ſo excellently fitted to this End, to heal our Impotency; which is not <hi>Natural</hi> but <hi>Moral.</hi> And God would not appoint us Means, which ſhould be altogether in vain.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> O. of the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Sin and Grace. <hi>p. 14.</hi>
               </note>
               <q>Grace is tender'd unto Men in the preaching of the Goſpel, to enable them to perform, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with that which God requires. For altho we know not the Way and Means, of the effectual Communications of Grace unto the Souls of Men: <hi>This is certain,</hi> That Grace is ſo tender'd in the Preaching of the Goſpel, that none go without it, none are deſtitute of its Aids and Aſſiſtance, but thoſe alone who <hi>by a Free Act of their own Wills,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See to the like pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, Mr. <hi>Howe</hi>'s <hi>Bleſſedneſs of the Righteous,</hi> ch. 17. &amp;</note> do refuſe and reject it. <hi>Ye will not come unto me, that you may have Life.</hi> And all Unbelievers have, or may have Experience of this in themſelves, that they do <hi>voluntarily</hi> refuſe the Aſſiſtance of Grace, which is offer'd for their Deliverance. <hi>Therefore is their Deſtruction of themſelves.</hi>—The common Grace<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Tears,</hi> p. 53. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend. <hi>p.</hi> 192.</note> which is generally afforded to them, who live under the Goſpel, extends ſo far as that they have thereby a <hi>Day</hi> allow'd them to provide for their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36181:11"/> Peace. Now though this Grace is not yet certainly Saving, yet it tends to that which is ſo; and none have cauſe to deſpair, but that being duly improv'd and comply'd with, it may end in it. It is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid to ſuch, (as live under the Goſpel,) they are <hi>to work out their Salvation with Fear and Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling,</hi> for this reaſon, that God works, or <hi>is working in them,</hi> i.e. ſtatedly and continually is at work, or is alway ready to work in them, <hi>to will and to do,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>of his own good Pleaſure,</hi> 2 Phil. 12.13. <hi>The matter fails not on his part.</hi> He <hi>will</hi> work on in order to Salvation, if <hi>they</hi> work in that way of Subordinate Co-operation, which his Command, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of their own caſe oblige them unto.—The Impotence therefore of the Will, lies in its<note n="*" place="margin">D. <hi>Bates</hi>'s Harmony of the D. Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, in <hi>Octavo.</hi> p. 63.</note> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy. This is the meaning of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſpeaking of Unclean Perſons, <hi>That their Eyes are full of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and they cannot ceaſe from Sin.</hi> 'Tis from their own Fault <hi>alone,</hi> that they are without Power. Therefore the Scripture repreſents Man to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, weak but wicked. His diſabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Supernatural Good, ariſes from an inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Affection to that which is ſenſual.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Let me add, if this Holy Word (animated by the Divine Spirit,) be not effectual to our Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thoſe means which are more <hi>Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,</hi> are not like to be ſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.22, 23, 24. <hi>They Rebelled againſt God, and would not believe his Word, or Truſt in his Salvation; though he commanded the Clouds from above, and opened the Doors of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and rained Manna for them to Eat, and gave them the Corn of Heaven.</hi> Their Victuals came out of the Clouds, and their Water cut of a Rock, and yet theſe Miracles did not Convert them. Neither the Miracles of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or thoſe of our Bleſſed Lord,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36181:12"/> were ſufficient in their time. In ſome Places our Lord wrought Miracles, and yet they deſired him to be gone out of their Coaſts: And when he was on the Croſs, they jeared him with his Miracles, though they could not but acknowledg them; <hi>he ſaved o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, himſelf he cannot; let him now come down from the Croſs, and we will believe.</hi> After the Miraculous Feeding of Two Thouſand with Five Loves and Two Little Fiſhes,<note place="margin">John 6.14, 22, 26, 30.</note> the People were aſtoniſhed, and ſaid one to another, <hi>This is he that ſhould come;</hi> this doubtleſs is the expected and long looked for <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias;</hi> and would have taken him by force, and made him King: And yet I think the very next Day, at leaſt within a Day or Two, when he told them they followed him only for the Loaves, they ſay unto him, <hi>What Sign ſheweſt thou that we ſhould believe?</hi> What work doſt thou? As if he had never wrought a Miracle before.<note place="margin">Luk. 16.31.</note> Yea, our Lord hath told us, <hi>If we will not hear</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets, neither would we believe, though one ſhould riſe from the Dead.</hi> Though one of your Acquaintance who Periſhed in his Sins, ſhould appear at Midnight in a Frightful Shape, and warn thee in particular by his Example, to take heed of Youthful Luſts, and not continue one Hour longer ſo near to endleſs and intolerable Miſery, as is every Impenitent Sinner? Should he tell thee, that he once made a Mock of Sin, and a Jeſt of Hell, and a Scorn of Godlineſs, as thou doſt? That he did not believe there was ſuch a Holy, Terrible God, as now he finds; or that it would be ſo fearful a thing to fall into his Hands? but now he feels the Word of God to be true; and that for a Fooliſh Luſt, he hath the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of a Miſerable Eternity. If ſuch Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings were given, they would not awaken Men to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36181:12"/> Repentance, unto whom the Preaching of the Word is not effectual. We read, that after the Reſurrection of <hi>Lazarus</hi> from the Dead, they that knew him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and knew he was raiſed again,<note place="margin">John 11.53.</note> and Converſed with him afterwards, were not Converted to believe on Chriſt; for <hi>from that very Day</hi> of his Raiſing <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> the High-Prieſts, and Scribes, and Rulers, and People, took Council how they might put him to Death. The like may be ſaid concerning the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>And how many do we ſee brought to the very brink of the Grave, within a ſtep of Death and Hell, both in their own apprehenſion, and in the judgment of others, who upon an unexpected Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, (not unlike a Reſurrection,) have been far from being reclaimed and bettered afterwards? Their forc'd Repentance vaniſheth, when the fear of dying ceaſeth. It is the Miniſtry of the Word, which is the <hi>ordinary</hi> Method that God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for our Sanctification; and if that be not effectual, theſe extraordinary Methods would not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It remains to be conſidered, That if this Word become the effectual means of our Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we muſt carefully attend, and <hi>take heed</hi> unto it. The Original imports to <hi>obſerve narrowly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 130.3.</note> with great exactneſs; we muſt ſtill have it in our Eye, that we may form our Deſigns, regulate our Affections, and order our Ways accordingly.<note place="margin">Joſh. 1.8.</note> We muſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preſerve it as a Treaſure, and watchfully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it as a Rule; we muſt <hi>hide it in our Hearts,</hi> verſe 11. A competent knowledge of this Word, and diligent endeavour to encreaſe it, is manifeſtly ſuppoſed;<note place="margin">Heb. 2.1.</note> and that we <hi>give earneſt heed to the things
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36181:13"/> we Read or Hear, leſt at any time we let them ſlip.</hi> We muſt ſtudy the Mind of God in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; wait on the Publick Preaching of it; conſider its Tendency and Uſe, as able to make us Wiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Salvation.<note place="margin">Col. 3.16.</note> We ſhould ponder it in our Hearts, and endeavour to preſerve it there, that it may co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit and dwell <hi>with</hi> us,<note place="margin">Jer. 15.16.</note> and <hi>in</hi> us, and be unto us <hi>the Joy</hi> and <hi>Rejoycing of our Hearts:</hi> Yielding up our ſelves unto the Power of Truth, that we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience its Holy Efficacy to all the Ends for which God hath appointed it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is firſt, and moſt obviouſly to be Collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from what hath been ſaid, is the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs</hi> and <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of the <hi>Holy Scriptures.</hi> What excellent Knowledge may be found there, for the cure of our Ignorance? What Sanctifying Influence, for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying of our Hearts and Ways? What Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Strength to fix our Wavering Minds, and heal our Unſetledneſs? How certain and Divine are its Inſtructions? How Pure and Spiritual, and yet Plain and Expreſs, are its Precepts? What pungent and ſmart Reproofs? what inviting Promiſes? what terrifying Threatnings, are imployed in this Word? to lead us into the way of Life, and ſave us from the Paths of the Deſtroyer? How fitly do the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it anſwer its Name?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.18. Rom. 1.16. Pſal. 110.2. Heb. 4.12.</note> of <hi>the Power of God,</hi> and <hi>the Rod of his Strength, the Power of God to the Salvation of the Soul? It is quick and powerful, ſharper than a Two-Edged Sword,</hi> to pierce and wound by Conviction. It is the <hi>Word of God's Grace,</hi> to heal thoſe Wounds;<note place="margin">Act. 20.32 1 Tim. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>able to build us up, and give us an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance among them that are Sanctified.</hi> What Sins are to be avoided, how Temptations are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, how Boſom Luſts are to be Mortified, and a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36181:13"/> Pure, Acceptable Worſhip to be performed, and what otherwiſe is neceſſary to the pleaſing of God, and Communion with him, is taught us in this Word.</p>
            <p>Hereby we are acquainted with our Sin and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and told the only way of our Recovery and Happineſs. The Malicious Arts and Stratagems of the Devil are here unfolded; hence we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed how to conceive of God, how to approach to him, converſe with him, and reſemble him. Our Steps are hereby directed by unerring Light; our Purpoſes ſetled, and our Courſe ſtated; and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections given us how to uſe our Selves, and all we have for the Service of our Maker, Redeemer and Sanctifier. By taking heed to this Light, we are ſafely led out of thoſe Labyrinths, where others have loſt their way, and may prevent ſtumbling into the Pit of Deſtruction, into which others fall. All the Doctrins and Precepts of this Word, tend to our Healing and Recovery; to promote the perfection and felicity of our Nature; to bring us to the beſt kind of <hi>Life</hi> for the preſent, in reſpect of duty to God, comfort to our Selves, and uſefulneſs unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: And this in the expectation of the Heavenly Reward: enabling us in ſome meaſure to partake of the Earneſt, and enjoy the Fore-taſtes of it. In ſhort, It is by this Word that we believe in Chriſt, and have hope towards God, and are enabled to love him, and ſo to dwell in Love. Our <hi>Faith,</hi> our <hi>Hope,</hi> our <hi>Love</hi> to God and Chriſt, are all begun, cheriſhed and maintained by the influence of this Word. To this we owe that <hi>Faith</hi> whereby we are vitally united to the Son of God; that <hi>Hope</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all our Grace flouriſheth; and that <hi>Love</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are Fruitful. For as by Faith we have a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36181:14"/> Spiritual Life, by Hope we gather Strength, and by Love we become active in all the Fruits of Holy O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This will juſtifie the extraordinary <hi>Eſteem</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> that Good Men have for <hi>the Word of God.</hi> Who, after ſuch experience of its cleanſing Virtue, but muſt profeſs, that the Sayings of this Book are <hi>Faithful,</hi> and <hi>True,</hi> and <hi>Worthy of all Acceptation? more to be deſired than Gold, than much Fine Gold, ſweeter than the Hony and the Hony-Comb?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.93, 97.</note> 
               <hi>O how love I thy Law!</hi> ſaith <hi>David, It is my Meditation all the Day. I will never forget thy Precepts, for by them thou haſt quickened me.</hi> O that this Law might be continually within my Heart, to enlighten, counſel and refreſh me! that it may dwell richly in me; be always <hi>an Ornament of Grace to my Head, and a Chain of Gold about my Neck; Health to my Navel, and Marrow to my Bones!</hi> I heard its Voice, I felt its Power, and beheld its glorious Beauty, and ſo have been changed into the ſame Image; and ſhall I not love it? If any ſhould ſeem to wonder, and think ſuch Eſtimations and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ſtrange, you may anſwer with the Man born Blind, <hi>John</hi> 9.30. <hi>This is a marvellous thing, that you know not what it is,</hi> or why I ſo much prize and love it, when <hi>it hath opened my Eyes.</hi> I was Spiritually Dead and Defiled, and by this Word I received quickning and cleanſing. No wonder therefore, if I account all things but Droſs and Dung in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this Knowledge.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.7, 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. What <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> ſhould they expreſs, whoſe Hearts have been ſeaſoned with Holy Principles and Affections <hi>betimes;</hi> and their Way cleanſed by the Word of God? If through the Knowledge of Chriſt, you have eſcaped the Pollutions that are in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36181:14"/> World, through Youthful Luſts, (when ſo many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are thereby Drowned in the Gulph of Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,) ſhould you not be very Thankful? When you behold Multitudes who wallow in the Mire, and take Pleaſure in the ways of Sin, are regardleſs of God and Chriſt, and the Eternal World, you may ſay, I was as Mad as they, or ſhould certainly have been ſo, if Free Grace had not prevented. What Gratitude do I owe to my Redeemer, and his Mighty Spirit, who makes me thus to differ! Many of you can look back with Joy and Praiſe upon the <hi>Early Experience</hi> you have had of this kind. You can reflect how <hi>early</hi> God began with your Souls, <hi>ſo early,</hi> that your Baptiſm ſeemed to have had its ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and influence preſently; <hi>ſo early</hi> with ſome, that you cannot tell the very time when God firſt began. Others can remember the ſpecial Inſtruments whom God imployed from time to time to do them good; by what careful and prudent Education,<note place="margin">Prov. 4.4.</note> by what uſeful Examples of Holy and Affectionate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, by what convincing Sermons,<note place="margin">Ch. 5.3, 4.</note> by what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wak'ning Providences, by what repeated Motions and Strivings of the Spirit of the Grace, you were brought to the knowledg of your Sin and Duty, and enabled to own and avow your <hi>Baptiſmal Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> and ſeriouſly out of choice come under the Bond of it. To which Purpoſe <hi>David</hi> acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.2, 7. <hi>O my Soul, thou haſt ſaid to the Lord, thou art my Lord, therefore I will bleſs thee, who hast given me Counſel,</hi> and enabled me to receive it; who haſt enlightened my Darkneſs, removed my Prejudices, cleanſed me from my Pollutions, ſoftned my hard Heart, ſubdued my Enmity and Diſaffection to thee, and made me willing in the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36181:15"/> Day of thy Power, to come to Chriſt that I might have Life and Healing by him. <hi>Lord how is it that thou doſt manifeſt thy Self to me, and not unto the World!</hi> That I ſhould be quickned and cleanſed, while others are left under Spiritual Defilement and Death.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What need have <hi>Superiors</hi> to be careful and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent to bring <hi>Young Perſons</hi> under their Charge, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the <hi>Word of God?</hi> It is mentioned not only to the Praiſe of Young <hi>Timothy,</hi> but of thoſe who were concerned in his Education, that <hi>he knew the Holy Scriptures from his Childhood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.15</note> 
               <hi>i.e.</hi> thoſe of the Old Teſtament, for ſcarce any other were then written when he was a Child. He was alſo acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with what was neceſſary to be known concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as is mentioned in the ſame Verſe, under the Expreſſion of <hi>the Faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Women and Children had then the Scriptures in a Language they underſtood; for his Grandmother <hi>Lois</hi> and his Mother <hi>Eunice</hi> inſtructed him very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the knowledge of God and Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Debauchery of Youth is very much owing to the want of good Principles inſtilled into their Minds in their Tender Years: By that means they are a more eaſie Prey to the Devil; having little or nothing to oppoſe, to the Snares he lays for them, or to their own corrupt Inclinations. You therefore that give up your Children to God by Baptiſm in Infancy, you ſeem to profeſs a Deſire they ſhould be <hi>his</hi> as ſoon as <hi>yours;</hi> you ſolemnly ingage and promiſe to bring them up in the Nurture and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of the Lord; but how falſe to God and them muſt you appear, if you do not ſeaſon them with Holy Principles betimes! if when you know they have Immortal Souls to Save, and an Eternal
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36181:15"/> Bleſſedneſs to obtain, and endleſs Miſery to eſcape, yet bring them up in <hi>Ignorance,</hi> without that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Knowledge that muſt make them wiſe to Salvation. If you do not inſtruct them in the Rules and Obligations of their Duty, that they may <hi>know the God of their Fathers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chr. 28.9</note> 
               <hi>and ſerve him with a perfect Heart.</hi> If you do not mind them of the Evil of Sin, the Uncertainty of this Life, and the Aſſurance of an Everlaſting State, of the Truth, and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of the Fall of Man, of the way of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation to God, and the Participation of his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If you do not inculcate theſe plain and neceſſary Truths upon them; if you do not bring them to the publick Worſhip; teach them how to ſpend the Lords Day; obſerve their particular Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Corruptions, and Temptations, and apply your ſelves accordingly with Wiſdom and Seriouſneſs for their good.</p>
            <p>Of all others you have the moſt Power over them, and Intereſt in them; none have ſuch Advantages and Opportunities to inſtruct and perſuade them as you. None are under ſo many Obligations of Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Intereſt of every ſort as you. It is therefore Unnatural and Unexcuſable to neglect it.</p>
            <p>You are not eaſily Apprehenſive how much your preſent Comfort is concerned in it; for if while they are Young, you are negligent in <hi>your</hi> Duty to them, they are likely enough when grown up, to fail of <hi>theirs</hi> to you. And it is but juſt they ſhould not know their Duty to <hi>You,</hi> if you do not inſtruct them in theirs to <hi>God.</hi> Theſe <hi>Arrows</hi> (to which they are compared in Scripture,<note place="margin">Prov. 22.6. Deut. 4.9. — 11.19.</note> and happy is he that hath his Quiver full of them,) ſhould be directed right at firſt, for accordingly they are like to Fly after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36181:16"/> It may fall out otherwiſe, but uſually the gracious or vicious Habits of the Firſt Age are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the next; and the after Converſation is ſuitable to the Education of Childhood and Youth. Beſides the Sin and Miſchief which you may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. For we know not at what Period of Time a Child comes to the uſe of Reaſon; and ſo cannot tell when God will impute their Follies, nor whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will tend; or what Impreſſions they may leave. But when he does not impute them to Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, it may be he will ſo far, as to cauſe Sickneſs, or an haſty Death. And therefore they ſhould be inſtructed in their Duty, <hi>ſo ſoon as capable,</hi> and be reſtrained from the material Parts of any Evil, even evil Words, which they underſtand not.</p>
            <p>Before I diſmiſs this Head, let me mind you that are <hi>Maſters of Families,</hi> that you ought thus care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to inſtruct your Younger Servants, the care of whoſe Souls is committed to you by the Providence of God: Your own ſafety and comfort, and the good ſucceſs of your Civil affairs, is concerned in it, as well as your Duty.<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>H. Palmer.</hi> Dr. <hi>H. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſon,</hi> on Job 13.26. <hi>p.</hi> 17.</note> An Eminent Preacher in his time, upon a like occaſion, in a Sermon at <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermanbury,</hi> made mention of a memorable Paſſage to this purpoſe. That in the beginning of the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Rebellion,</hi> there were ſome Popiſh <hi>Servants</hi> cut the Throats of thoſe who had formerly been their <hi>Maſters,</hi> telling them that <hi>they ſhould have taught them better.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Somewhat of <hi>Direction</hi> and <hi>Counſel</hi> I would now add unto the Younger ſort. Let me therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To make a Pauſe, to ſtop a while, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think your ſelves: Employ ſome time in a ſerious
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36181:16"/> Conſideration of your Hearts and Ways, according to this Word of God. Think, what ſort of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures you are, and how you came into this World? Who was the Author of your Beings, and the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of all things? What did he make you for? but to Glorifie and Enjoy him? How wretchedly uncapable you have rendered your ſelves of both? And in order to your Relief, what is to be done on your part, and what may be hoped for on God's; and how remedileſs your Caſe is, if this Affair be not begun to be tranſacted before the only time is paſt, wherein it may be done. O try your Reaſon, and uſe it in ſuch Reflections. Think in what a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition you were born; how you have lived; what you have done, and what you now are; whether you are going, and where you muſt ſhortly be: Think what your ſinful Folly hath already coſt you; what you have loſt, and the manifold Hurts and Miſchiefs you have received by it. What unthrifty Bargains you have made, and what is the bitter Fruit of thoſe things whereof you are now aſhamed. The Devil himſelf cannot perſuade you, but <hi>you muſt Die;</hi> and you dare not ſay or think that there is not an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting <hi>Heaven</hi> or <hi>Hell:</hi> You therefore ſometimes wiſh to die the Death of the Righteous. And will you not conſider a little, how impoſſible that is, without being like them while you live?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Endeavour clearer <hi>Apprehenſions,</hi> and a better <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> of the <hi>Religion</hi> you profeſs, as to the Evidence of its Principles, the Nature, Grounds and Reaſons of it. That you may know your own Caſe, and what it is to be a Chriſtian, and what the neceſſary change does imply, and how it is to be wrought. That you may know the <hi>God</hi> from whom
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36181:17"/> you have revolted; whom you are to obey as your Sovereign Ruler, and to enjoy as your chief good. That you may know the <hi>Saviour,</hi> that muſt befriend you for the Pardon of Sin, and for Eternal Life. That you may know the <hi>Holy-Ghoſt,</hi> the Sanctifier, by whom you muſt be Enlightened, Quickened and Renewed. How can you love and obey your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, if you know him not? what he is, and how he will be ſerved? How can you believe on Chriſt, if you know not who he is, or what he hath Done and Suffered, Purchaſed, Promiſed, Offered, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, and is ready to be, and do, and give? How can you bewail your Sin and Miſery? Loath your ſelves, and ſeek for Grace, if you continue Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of ſuch things as theſe? It is by the Light of Holy Knowledge you muſt be recovered; you are <hi>loſt</hi> and periſhing,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.4.</note> while this <hi>Goſpel is hid</hi> from you. If you are not ſenſible of your own Ignorance and Diſeaſe, and where is the Remedy; how will you come to Chriſt as your Teacher and Phyſician?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To this end, diligently <hi>ſtudy the Holy Scriptures,</hi> and attend the <hi>Publick Preaching</hi> of the Word,<note place="margin">Deut. 17.18.</note> 
               <hi>with ſuitable Deſires and Deſigns.</hi> Apprehend the weight of the matters treated of, and know that it is for your Life: You know not the advantage of an affectionate Study of the Holy Scriptures. While the <hi>Ethiopian Eunuch</hi> was reading in the Prophet <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 8.26.</note> though he underſtood it not, God did ſo far reward and bleſs him, that he ſent <hi>Philip</hi> to inſtruct him farther, and his Converſion to the Faith was the Iſſue of it. When ever you hear the Word Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, remember in whoſe Name, and upon what Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand the Meſſage comes.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:36181:17"/>
            <p>Therefore lay aſide every Prejudice,<note place="margin">Jam. 1.21. Luk. 8.18. Act. 10.33.</note> and place your ſelves as under the Eye of your All-ſeeing Judge. We that ſpeak to you in the name of the Lord, have very much to blame our ſelves for, God knows, that we are not Serious enough, and Compaſſionate enough to the Souls of Men: (not adapting our ſelves to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities and Neceſſities of the Younger and more Ignorant ſort.) Alas! we ſee and know but little, and feel leſs of the great important things we ſpeak of. And though we hope we find Mercy to be Faithful, yet how ſhort do we come of that Affection and Vigor, and ſerious Importunity, which the caſe of Sinful Periſhing Souls doth need? How unlike thoſe that know the Terrors of the Lord, the value of an Immortal Soul, and the nearneſs of Eternity? How unbecoming thoſe who ſpeak every Lord's Day unto Men and Women, unto whom <hi>we</hi> may never ſpeak more? And it may be ſuch and ſuch of <hi>you</hi> ſhall never hear a Sermon more; take heed therefore how you hear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Be moſt <hi>Importunate</hi> with God for <hi>the Spirit of Holineſs and Sanctification.</hi> He alone can reſtore Life to thy Dead Soul, and conquer the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of thy Heart againſt Holineſs. <hi>For we are Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Waſhing of Regeneration, and by the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 3 Tit. 5. Beg the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, with an Earneſtneſs anſwerable to your Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of what you ask; that he may be a Living Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, to cauſe you to walk in his Statutes, and keep his Commandments.<note place="margin">Ezek. 36.26, 27.</note> Forgiveneſs of Sin is not all that you need; you are Diſeaſed and Defiled, and need to be Cured and Cleanſed. If you ask the Holy Spirit with an apprehenſion and feeling of your need of his powerful Influence, you may ſupplicate
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36181:18"/> and plead the Promiſe in Hope, that God will more readily grant you, than any Father upon Earth gives Bread to his Children.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.6. Chap. 7.11.</note> 
               <hi>They that ſeek him early and earneſtly, ſhall find him.</hi> Our Lord is exalted to give Repentance, and Saving Faith; his Powerful Grace can ſubdue the moſt Impetuous Luſts of Youth. You may be earneſt and importunate with God for theſe things; he does not require or expect you ſhould be contented to periſh in your Filthineſs and Unbelief, deſpairing of Helo, as if the caſe of Man were like that of Devils: He requires you to Hope, and is pleaſed with it.<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>How</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer's Tears, <hi>p.</hi> 118.</note> And if you find any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Strivings of this Bleſſed Spirit, in anſwer to Prayer, cheriſh every Beginning of it, as an Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of more. Be thankful for every Beam of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Light, from the God of all Grace; it may prove the dawning of a more perfect Day. Beg that this mighty Spirit would open your <hi>Eyes</hi> and <hi>Hearts,</hi> that being convinced of the certainty and reality of the Goſpel Revelation, by the view of its ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs to your caſe, and the many glorious advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages that are offered by it, you may be brought to love it as Amiable; and yield up your ſelves entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in compliance with it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Take heed of <hi>Declining</hi> after good and <hi>hopeful Beginnings.</hi> How many Young Perſons have begun in the Spirit, and ended in the Fleſh? Light hath ſhone in upon their Minds; they have been under awakning Convictions by the Word; ſtrong Affections have been excited by it; they delighted to hear and read it; they kept up a courſe of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Prayer for ſome time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet have after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards fallen away to a Vicious Life. It may be they had not conſidered and counted the coſt of being
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36181:18"/> Reſolved Chriſtians; what they muſt abandon and forſake; what pleaſing Temptations they muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void and reſiſt; what inſtances of Self-denial they muſt conſent to, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore by the Sollicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Sophiſtry, or Jears of their Old Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, through the Subtilty of Satan, and the Power of Youthful Luſts, they have been intangled again with the Pollutions of the World, and the Strong Man hath re-enter'd the Houſe, with Seven Evil-Spirits worſe than himſelf.</p>
            <p>How Miſerable is the caſe of ſuch, after they have been enlightned, and in part delivered,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.26.</note> who return to their former Bondage, and are <hi>led Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive by the Devil at his Will!</hi> They were not far from the Kingdom of God; they ſeemed to conſent to be the Lord's; they were almoſt perſwaded to take the Yoke of Chriſt upon them, as his reſolved Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers: but now have taken leave of him, and are at the Command of Satan; <hi>his Will is theirs:</hi> If he bid them think as little of God as they can deſpiſe the Holy Scripture, make light of Sabbaths and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and all good Counſel, <hi>they do it.</hi> If he bid them gratifie their Carnal Appetites, indulge their Senſual Inclinations, and frequent ſuch and ſuch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnaring Company, <hi>they do it.</hi> They are led Captive by him <hi>at his Will.</hi> With what Hearty Compaſſion ſhould we think and ſpeak of the caſe of ſuch! and many ſuch there be. But if you are not harden'd through the deceitfulneſs of ſin, paſt all feeling, I would feign ask you, whether you are not yet <hi>willing</hi> to return? If Mercy may be had, and you may yet be recovered out of the Snare of the Devil; Dare you ſolemnly and expreſly in ſo many Words, take leave of Chriſt, and bid him farewel for ever?
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36181:19"/> Are you content to forfeit his Favour, and throw up all hopes of it, and venture his Eternal Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? Would you not yet return, if God would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you? If there be Balm in <hi>Gilead,</hi> and a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician there, that you may be healed? May I not tell you, in the Name of Chriſt, that <hi>there is;</hi> and that if you return with your whole Heart, (you eſpecially, who are the Children of Holy Parents,) he will yet receive you: He will meet you half-way, and bid you welcom.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.1, 2, 3. Iſa. 55.6, 7, 8.</note> He will heal your Backſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and blot out your Tranſgreſſions, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your Iniquities no more. He pawns the Authority of his own great Name for this, <hi>Three</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times in one Verſe, to aſſure you of it, <hi>Zach.</hi> 1.3.<note place="margin">Prov. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>Turn ye at my Reproof, and I will pour out my Spirit upon you,</hi> is the Voice of Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>I might likewiſe direct you in your Addreſſes to God for his Purifying Grace, to Eye <hi>the Blood of * Chriſt,</hi> as the procuring cauſe of your Sanctification; and the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> the Purchaſe of that Blood, as the great Sanctifier of Souls. I might urge you far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, * that with an hearty abhorrence of every Sin, you would penitently and thankfully renew the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> you made with God in your <hi>Baptiſm, yielding your Selves to the Lord,</hi> as the moſt ſolemn and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Tranſaction of your whole Lives. And be ſure * keep out of the way of <hi>Temptation</hi> as much as you can, endeavouring to avoid thoſe particular Snares by which you are moſt eaſily overcome. Pretend not a Reſolution againſt the Sin, if you are willing to look upon the Temptation; to walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the brink of the River, and to come near the door of that Houſe, into which you know you muſt not enter. It is impoſſible a Man ſhould love to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36181:19"/> abide by a Temptation for a good end, or without unſpeakable Hazard. It is vain Confidence on your own Strength, to come as near Sin as you durſt, and the Event does commonly prove it ſo. Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially * ſee that you well imploy your Time upon <hi>the Lords Day;</hi> and take heed to your * <hi>Company</hi> all the Week. Few of the Younger ſort Miſcarry, but date their Sin and Ruin from the neglect of this Counſel. * Begin with God every <hi>Morning,</hi> by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Prayer,</hi> and Reading ſome part of the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> with ſome Practical Affectionate Book, if but for a quarter of an Hour; it would leave a ſerious Tincture on the Mind, and a good Savour on the Heart, and be of uſe to antidote you againſt Temptation, and to preſerve a Holy frame all the Day. But * never deſiſt your diligent <hi>Endeavours,</hi> till you come to <hi>walk with God</hi> in his Love and Fear, and as under his Eye, all the Day long: That the pleaſing of God may become the Buſineſs, and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of your Lives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Do not <hi>delay</hi> Compliance with theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, but preſently ſet about it; can you begin too ſoon to cleanſe your Hearts and Ways? Is it <hi>too ſoon</hi> to be reconciled to God, and delivered from the danger of Damnation? Can you attain Peace of Conſcience, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt, and a well grounded Hope of Eternal Life <hi>too ſoon?</hi> If you languiſh'd under a noiſom Diſtemper that threatned your Life, would you imagin you could be healed too ſoon? And how much Sin and Miſchief, Shame and Sorrow, and bitter Repentance may you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, by taking heed unto the Word of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times? How much larger Opportunities for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying of God, have <hi>Young Converts,</hi> than <hi>late</hi> Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36181:20"/> though they be Sincere? What Advantages never to be retrieved have they loſt, who have out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinned their Youth? becauſe their Time is gone, and can never be recalled. What Honour may you bring to God, who remember your Creator in the days of your Youth? What Ornaments to your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion may you prove? Of what uſefulneſs unto others in this World? being filled with the Spirit of God. What attainments in Grace, and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt,<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Charnock,</hi> Vol. 2. p. 57, 58.</note> and what additional degrees of Glory may you reach? You may grow to a greater Stature, being new born in Youth, and bring forth more and better Fruit in Old Age: You will have a longer time of Peace of Conſcience, and of the Comforts of the Spirit; much ſweeter fore-taſtes of Heaven, and improved meetneſs for it. You may lay up Treaſures of Experience to confute the Devil, if he aſſault you on a Death-Bed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is it nothing to deſpiſe all theſe advantages of an Early Piety? to ſecure the comfort and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs for the future part of your Lives? Is it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be prepared for a ſudden Death? and to provide againſt the Pangs and Sorrowful Reflections of a Death-bed? Is it nothing, when you come to Die, to review your former Life with Joy? ſaying, <hi>Lord! remember how I have ſerved thee, the God of my Fathers, from my Childhood,</hi> and <hi>Youth!</hi> Is it nothing to bring God greater Glory in this World? and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a more weighty and ſparkling Crown of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the next? Have you not been often told, how much more difficult your Repentance and Converſion to God will hereafter be, than now, if you ſhould be ſpared ſome Years longer? Are your Hearts like to be better by longer continuance in Sin? Will the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36181:20"/> of God be leſs provoked? will it not be more? Will the Devil have leſs advantage againſt you, when he hath had ſo much longer Poſſeſſion? <hi>To Day, while it is called to Day, if you will hear his Voice, harden not your Hearts.</hi> It is ſome hardning of your Hearts, not to hearken to his Voice <hi>this day:</hi> It is one ſtep more towards final Impenitence and Unbelief, againſt which there is no Remedy provided in the Goſpel. How hardly was that Man Cured,<note place="margin">Mark 9.29.</note> who was poſſeſſed with a Devil from his Childhood? The more you are alienated from the Life of God, the harder will be your Recovery.</p>
            <p>And how much greater is the provocation againſt God, by every ſuch Delay? How aggravated and diſpleaſing is your baſe ingratitude againſt the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God, and a Merciful Redeemer? You reject his preſent Call, ſlight his Kindneſs, and refuſe his Love, and in effect tell him, that though you have no mind to periſh, but that one time or other before you die, you will accept it; that yet you have other Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for the preſent to mind; it will be time enough for that when you are more at leiſure. Your Youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Luſts now call you, your Secular Affairs and Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the World now call you to other Thoughts; and <hi>theſe</hi> ſhal l be <hi>firſt</hi> minded and ſerved. Your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate Phyſician offers his Help, and promiſes a Cure, if you will but hearken and ſubmit to him: You tell him in effect, that you like your Leproſie, and are in love with your Diſeaſe: You care not to be recovered to Health: you will not as yet be Purged and Healed; though one time or other you intend to call for his Aſſiſtance. May he not moſt juſtly ſay unto you, <hi>Let him that is filthy, be filthy ſtill. You would not be purged from your filthineſs, therefore you ſhall not, till you die.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:36181:21"/>
            <p>How bitter will be the Thoughts of theſe repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Calls neglected? What cold Horror, and Shiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Dread ſhall ſeize thee on a Bed of Languiſhing? which ſome may take for <hi>true Repentance.</hi> But, Oh how little of <hi>that,</hi> which by a large Charity we hope is ſo, may the Righteous God accept? and who can tell whether he does or no? For ſuch Men ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the brink of the Grave, and ſtepping into Hell, and know it is as much as their Souls are worth, preſently to make Peace with God by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Repentance.</p>
            <p>No wonder then if they let fall ſome little Drops of a beginning Sorrow; if they have ſome extort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reſolutions of Living better; ſome ſudden Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe and Regret for thoſe Sins, that they are now like to be Damned for; ſome quick and raſh Vows of an Awaken'd Conſcience; with ſome Confuſion of Face under the Fears of Death and Judgment. But at ſuch a time, it is hard to diſtinguiſh between Religious Sighs and Natural Groans; or ſeparate their Repenting Cries for Mercy, from their Howl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings on their Beds through Bodily Pain. 'Tis true, God may work Miracles of Mercy on ſuch Convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Sinners, who did not ſeek to him till the <hi>Eleventh</hi> Hour; but whether he will no, there is no Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty or Probability, but that he can if he pleaſe; which to Perſons in that condition, who fear an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Hell the next Hour, is a ſad uncomfortable Thought. No Man in his Wits that reads the Bible, would run the Hazard.</p>
            <p>If they have the uſe of Reaſon, and are not harden'd in Atheiſm and Infidelity, they cannot but fear and tremble: Peace and Proſperity may tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port Men; the Mouth of <hi>Conſcience</hi> may be ſtop'd
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36181:21"/> in Health by falſe Principles, and the Voice of Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Company; its ſecret Whiſpers may be drown'd by the noiſe and hurry of Buſineſs, or diverted, brib'd, and abus'd by the entertainments of Senſe, and the deceitfulneſs of Riches. But in Sickneſs and Affliction, when diſ-intangled from its Fetters, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will ſpeak its own Senſe; and it ever ſpeaks loudeſt in a time of Calamity: Then it will witneſs and accuſe, condemn and terrifie. All their Arts of Oblivion cannot make it ſilent; it will diſquiet them with Fears and Torments, which encreaſe at the approach of <hi>Death,</hi> and after Death are the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>Hell.</hi> For though, as one ſays, <hi>That</hi> may not be fully opened till the laſt Judgment, yet the Anguiſh of <hi>Conſcience</hi> is a part of Hell-Fire, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory to the Horrible Sentence of Dooms-day.</p>
            <p>Now, Is he <hi>his own Murderer,</hi> who would not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make Peace with God, when in danger of approaching Death? The like is he, who will defer this for <hi>one Day,</hi> becauſe every Day of ſuch delay is a Day of Danger; and ſo is he obliged by the ſame care for himſelf, and concern for his Soul, if he Sinned Yeſterday, to Repent to Day, leſt he be Dead to Morrow. For how many Perſons die Suddenly? (many have done ſo of late, and more may;) and who knows that he ſhall not? Thy Sick Neighbour may recover and live many Years, and he that is now in Health, may expire the next Hour. You are alſo uncertain of a tedious Sickneſs, to afford you the lingering forerunners of Death; or of ſuch a one, as ſhall not diſturb the Brain, and unfit for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Thoughts. The firſt Symptom of your laſt Sickneſs, may conclude your Life; you may not have time to complain or cry. <hi>Job</hi> 36.13, 14. <hi>They cry not when he bindeth them, they die in their Youth, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36181:22"/> their Life is among the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean.</hi> How groundleſs are the Expectations of arriving to Old-Age? The Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Tree does not every where flouriſh. Hardly one or Two of a great Multitude, lay down a Hoary Head in the Bed of the Grave. Very little Ripe Fruit is gathered into the Basket, in compariſon of the many Bloſſoms that fall to the Ground. Is not your Conſtitution in Youth more tender? and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently more ſubject to external Impreſſions, that may cauſe Sickneſs: While grown Branches can ſtand the ſhock of a Cold Winter, every Blaſt or Storm will ſpoil the Beauty of new blown Flowers. And yet though you know this, and therefore muſt grant your length of Days no ſurer than that of others, and your preſuming on the future equally hazardous, and without ground; you will not <hi>now</hi> Repent, and turn to God. It may be you Reſolve you <hi>will,</hi> if you live till <hi>hereafter;</hi> that is, you are content to to be Damned if you die before that time: And <hi>who knows what a Day may bring forth?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 27.1. Jam. 4.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Though you are now Strong and Healthful, in the heat and Wantonneſs of Youthful Blood, or in the ſtrength and vigour of your Age, and begin to have a throng of Worldly Buſineſs, may not the ſame be ſaid of ſome of thoſe who died the laſt Week? who it may be delayed their Repentance on the like grounds, and thought their own Death as improbable as you do yours; which is now ſo much the nearer, by how many Days you have ſurviv'd them. Is there any of you but would willingly Repent, and turn to God, one Day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you die? And who can be ſure to do that, who delays till <hi>to Morrow?</hi> I perſwade my ſelf, you cannot think that you ſhall be exempted from appearing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Bar of Chriſt, if you die in Youth: Or that thoſe Luſts and Sins that are Damning to Men of Forty,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36181:22"/> will not be reckon'd for by God, or hereafter puniſh'd, becauſe committed by one of Sixteen. Will you yet boldly put it to the venture?<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.11.</note> and <hi>Rejoyce O Young Man in thy Youth, and walk in the way of thy own Heart, and neither know nor conſider, that for all theſe things God will bring thee to Judgment.</hi> And how ſoon may you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Summons? every whit as ſoon as if you had lived many Years longer. To ſeveral Diſeaſes <hi>You</hi> are more obnoxious than Elder Perſons, to ſome that are now Reigning, and often prove Mortal, as you are more full of warm Blood, to catch the Infection; particularly the <hi>Small-Pox.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which Diſtemper it pleaſed God to viſit <hi>this young Gentleman,</hi> Mr. <hi>Richard Walter,</hi> in the Eighteenth Year of his Age; concerning whom, (as it will not be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſo) it cannot be expected I ſhould ſpeak much, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almoſt a Stranger to him, till the laſt Scene of his Life. When I was requeſted to joyn with ſome Friends in Prayer for him, and afterwards at his own Deſire viſited him, and prayed with him. I found him in a very Penitent and Serious frame, which I hope was not the bare effect of his having receiv'd the Sentence of Death in himſelf; not only becauſe during his whole Sickneſs, he diſcovered the like Temper of Mind, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he had the free Exerciſe of Reaſon, (which after ſome Days <hi>Delirium,</hi> God was pleaſed very obſervably to reſtore in anſwer to Prayer,) but becauſe he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been under very ſerious Impreſſions of what concern'd his Soul, and the Everlaſting World. Unto which purpoſe, the practical Books of that Great and Holy Man Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> were uſeful to him; as they have been unto Thouſands more. Theſe Impreſſions I hope did remain, and were now and then awaken'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd upon him, notwithſtanding the dangerous Snares and Temptations of Youth. His fervent and penitent
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36181:23"/> Supplications to Heaven, as the fruit of theſe, I hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> found Acceptance with the Father of Mercies, thro the Mediation of Chriſt: For at the very laſt he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> afraid or unwilling to Dye. Notwithſtanding that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> expreſt a very great Senſe of his Sin, he could yet ſay <q>I hope my Dear Redeemer hath enabled me to Repent and hath forgiven me. There is Pity in his Boſom, and Mercy in his Breaſt.</q> And ſo he went on, mentioning ſome Scriptures to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>There is one thing I would add, (which may be <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table</hi> and Exemplary, if God allow you the uſe of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon on a Sick Bed,) that before he died, he was willing to do ſomething to promote the Salvation of his Ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quaintance and Companions, as the beſt Expreſſion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Friendſhip to 'em, by exciting them to conſider thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Latter End, and prepare for the other World, wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we muſt have our unchangable, Eternal Abode. Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appear'd, when I ſpake to him on that Head, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Meſſages he deſir'd me to convey to ſome o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 'em, and by his moſt affectionate Wiſh, and <hi>Praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for his</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland of <hi>Barbadoes.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Parents,</hi> when I parted from him, <hi>viz. Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he might meet them in Heaven; where,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more and better Pleaſure in one Moment, than is to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> found in all the Enjoynments of this World for a Thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſand Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God grant that they, and all his Relations and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, ſuch eſpecially who have deſir'd this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, may wiſely improve his Deceaſe which admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred the occaſion. And may it be of ſome uſe to all the Younger ſort who heard it, or may now read it to help 'em to conſider, and remember the Divine Counſel o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Text, <hi>how Young Men may cleanſe their Ways, by taking heed unto the Word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
